Guide to the Joel Garreau Papers, 1954-1994
George Mason University Libraries
- Series 1: Edge City, 1959-February 1994
  - Redevelopment Arlington Virginia, August 1988 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    Documents about Arlington, Virginia. Documents include a Washington Post article "2 New Developments Endorsed for Arlington" by Evelyn Hsu, notes and a group of articles from New Dominion magazine about Ballston in Arlington.
  - Rosslyn Ballston, April-June 1989 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    Articles about the Washington Metropolitan Area. A Business Week article "Human Gene Therapy: After A Lot of Looking, Now The Leap" by John Carey and two Washington Post articles "Ballston: New Urban Atmosphere" by Evelyn Hsu and "Renewing Rockville: The City Moves Past Suburban Sprawl" by Roger K. Lewis.
  - Carnegie Deli, October 1987-September 1988 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    Documents about delicatessens. Material includes notes, a New York Times article "Lox on Both Their Houses" by Alan M. Dershowitz, a napkin and catering menu from the Carnegie Delicatessen and Restaurant, a letter to Garreau from Otterbine Barebo and advertisement about waterscaping and a Washington Post article "The Invasion of the Pastrami Slicers" by Paula Span.
  - Fairfax County Planning Virginia (Box 9, Folder 38)
    The rough draft of the second chapter of a book, the chapter is titled "Methodological Approach". The chapter has to do with development in Fairfax.
  - ASCA 1988 Northeast Regional Conference, October 1988 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    A large booklet of information for the Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture's 1988 Northeast Regional Conference, titled "The Endless City; It's Extension Growth and Decay". Also included is "The Corporatization and Decay of Public Urban Space" by Gerald L. Maffei and Walter V. Wendler.
  - Future Development Futurist Manifesto, Undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Documents about Futurism. Material includes "The Founding and Manifesto of Futurism", "Manifesto of the Futurist Painters", "Futurist Painting: Technical Manifesto 1910" and the Forward and Introduction of "The Real Thing: Imitation and Authenticity in American Culture, 1880-1940" by Miles Orvell. Theory
  - Fishman, May 1989-December 1990 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Documents by Robert Fishman about the evolution of cities. Material includes two copies of "America's New City: Megalopolis Unbound" from the Winter 1990 issue of The Wilson Quarterly and "Metropolis Unbound: The New City of the Twentieth Century". Theory
  - Economic Cores Development, August 1988-May 1989 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Documents and correspondence about economic cores development. Material includes "Aphorisms and Ideas Generated by the Mayor's Institute on Urban Design", the Fall 1988 issue of the RCL Co Comments on Management and Marketing For the Real Estate Industry, E. Wayne Angle's Tysons II business card and a Master's thesis "Prototype and Innovation: Case Studies in the Evolution of Mixed-Use Development" by Paul David Sehnert and Baird McCargo Standish. Theory
  - environment vs. Development, March 1989-December 1992 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Documents about the relationship between the environment and development. Material includes a Real Estate Review article "The Prospect for Rebound in the Commercial Real Estate Market" by William C. Wheaton and Raymond G. Torto, the May 1992 issue of The Institutional Real Estate Letter, a packet of information about metropolitan markets and their investment values, a Washington Post article "Searching for Survival: Saving the Parks Isn't Enough" by John Lancaster, the May 1990 issue of PERC Reports, an article from Reason magazine "Roots of Environmentalism" by William C. Dennis, a section of The Economist about the environment, a two part article from The New Yorker by Tony Hiss "Reflections: Encountering the Countryside" and the first and third drafts of a proposal titled "The Relationship Between Conserving the Natural Environment and Quality Community and Urban Development". Theory
  - Downtown, April-November 1988 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Documents about the development of downtowns. Material includes an article from Pitt Magazine "The Rise and Fall-and Rise-of Cities", a Wall Street Journal article :Urban Lab: Los Angeles Offers a Future Glimpse" by Frederick Rose, "Creating Great American Downtown in the 21st Century" by John Fondersmith, "A Proposed Strategy for a Portfolio of Land Investments in the Path of Urban Employer Emiration" by James A. Graaskamp, "America's Educational Failures: How Will They Affect Real Estate?" by Anthony Downs and "The Restless Urban Landscape: Economic and Sociocultural Change and the Transformation of Metropolitan Washington, DC" by Paul L. Knox. Theory
  - Gardens, September 1988-March 1989 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Documents about city gardens. Material includes a Progressive Architecture article "Garden in the Machine" by Mark Alden Branch, an advertisement for "The Poetics of Gardens" by Charles W. Moore, William J. Mitchell, and William Turnbull, Jr., a Washington Post article "Back to Eden: Images From the Landscape of the Imagined" by Henry Allen, a New York Times article "How Do New Gardens Grow? In Green Sand and Fantasy" by Daralice D. Boles, notes and a quote from Frederick Law Olmstead. Theory
  - Forests Cities, July 1985-January 1992 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Documents about forests. Material includes the January 1992 issue of National Woodlands, "The City" a transcript of an interview by Donald McDonald with Allan Temko and Arthur Naftalin, a memo about Lake States Regional Forest Resources Assessment, "Urban Development in Forests" by Henry H. Webster, a booklet titled "Forest Resources in the Northeast: Contribution to Economic Development and Social Well Being", a note to Garreau from Henry H. Webster and a copy of his article mentioned above. Theory
  - Computers, March 1988-November 1989 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Documents about computers. Material includes Wall Street Journal articles "Information and the Future of the City" and "Information and the Future of the City" by Peter F. Drucker, and "A Brave New World: Streams of 1s and 0s" by Michael W. Miller, Washington Post articles "Digital Imaging Revives Dreams of a Paperless Society" by John Burgess and "Va.'s Income Growth Outpaces Much of Nation" by John M. Berry, a Harper's Magazine article "Out My Computer Window" by Hugh Kenner, presentation slides about telecommuting, a National Geographic Magazine article "Images for the Computer Age" by Fred Ward and a transcript of James Burke's remarks to the American Institute of Architects at the May 1990 convention in Houston. Theory
  - Telework, April 1989 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    A paper by Gil Gordon and David L. Peterson about telework. Theory
  - De Tocqueville Biography Review, March 1989 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    "The Man Who Understood America the Best" by Max Lener, a book review of "Tocqueville: A Biography" by Andre Jardin. Theory
  - Culture and Vision, 1980-1985 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    Materials include the first three chapters of "VIA Culture and the Social Vision" and the first sixty nine pages of "Architecture for the Emerging American City". Theory
  - Communications Computers Community, June 1989-November 1991 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    Documents and correspondence about communications. Material includes a Wall Street Journal article "Digital Revolution" by Michael W. Miller, the Responsive Community's "The Responsive Communitarian Platform: Rights and Responsibilities", the October 17th 1991 Marketplace section of the Wall Street Journal, a Smithsonian Magazine article "Through the looking glass into an artificial world-via computer" by Doug Stewart, an invitation to the "Industry Symposium on Virtual Worlds Technology", "Intercommunications Technologies: Regional Variations in Postal Service Use in Sweden, 1870-1975" by Ronald Abler and Thomas Falk and "Intercommunications Technologies: The Development of Postal Services in Sweden" by Thomas Falk and Ronald Abler. Theory
  - Cultural Change, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Documents about cultural change. Material includes chapter 17 (Time-space compressions and the post modern condition) of "The Condition of Post modernity" by David Harvey and a draft of "The Culture Area Concept Reconsidered" by Clarence Mondale. Theory
  - T. Baerwald, May-June 1989 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Documents by and about Thomas J. Baerwald. Material includes "The Evolution of Suburban Downtowns in Midwestern Metropolises" by Thomas J. Baerwald, Baerwald's curriculum vitae, "Changing Sales Patterns in Major American Metropolises, 1963-1982" by Thomas J. Baerwald and "The Emergence of A New 'Downtown'" by Thomas J. Baerwald. Theory
  - Russel Baker Capitalism, January 1988-September 1990 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Documents about Capitalism and Russell Baker. Material includes "Markets and Morality" by Peter J. Hill in the January/February 1988 issue of PERC Viewpoints, a New Yorker article "Reflections: The Triumph of Capitalism" by Robert Heilbroner and an interview of Russel Baker about living in Leesburg, VA. Theory
  - Cemeteries-Cities (history of development), April 1981-July 1992 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Documents about city development and cemeteries. Material includes a Boston Globe article "Down on Main Street" by Peirce Lewis, chapter five (The Regulatory Mode) of "The Urban Millennium" by Josef W. Konvitz, an article from The Harvard Architecture Review "Space Is the American Mediator, or The Blocks of Ithaca: A Speculation" by Peter Smithson, "The Influence of the Foreign Heritage on the American City" from the Department of Housing and Urban Development and "A Toponymic Approach to the Geography of American Cemeteries" by Wilbur Zelinsky. Theory
  - Grady Clay, Civilization, Comparison of Cities, November 1980-August 1991 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Documents by and about Grady Clay, civilization, and the comparison of cities. Material includes the October 1988 issue of Planning Contents, a Washington Post article "The Generic Tour Guide" by Henry Mitchell, Planning Contents articles "Holdout" and "Arrival Zones" by Grady Clay, an article from MASS Journal of the School of Architecture and Planning "Megalopolis in Passing: The Function of Ephemeral Places" by Grady Clay, Grady Clay's business card, a note to Garreau from Grady Clay, "The Burn (Or Burned Over Area)", a Names Journal of the American Name Society article "A Few Good Words for Generic Places: Especially Those Here Today, Gone Tomorrow" by Grady Clay, "Ephemeral Places" an introduction to Design Quarterly issue 89 by Grady Clay, a Louisville Magazine article "Educated Eyes Scan Cities to Spot Evidence of Change" by Grady Clay, A Louisville Times article "Right down his alley" by Diane Kimbel, a Lexington Herald-Leader article "As Lexington grows, what will it become?" by Grady Clay, a Boston Globe Magazine article "The Hub and The City" by John King and an American Demographics article "In The Shadow of The Mall" by David Russell and Martha Russell. Theory
  - Christopher Alexander, May 1972-January 1990 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Documents by and about Christopher Alexander. Material includes a paper about Christopher Alexander by Nore Gallagher, the Encyclopedia of Art and Architecture entry for Christopher Alexander, a New Age Journal article "a clean, well-lighted place" by Jon Krakauer, a report on Christopher Alexander's potential fellowship at the John Simon Guggenhein Memorial Foundation, a Progressive Architecture article "Harmony and Wholeness" by Pilar Viladas about Christopher Alexander, "Beyond Humanism" an interview with Christopher Alexander, notes, "Christopher Alexander and The Pattern Language" by Benjamin Clavan, an Architectural Record article "Toward a personal workplace" by Christopher Alexander, Artemis Anninou, and Gary Black, "A City of Gardens: Pasadena Design Ordinance for Multi-Family Housing", "A Watershed in the History of Architecture" by Christopher Alexander, a transcript of an interview of Christopher Alexander by Garreau, "The Pattern Language and Its Enemies" by Kimberly Dovey, a book review by Kim Dovey of "A New Theory of Urban Design" by Christopher Alexander and others, a Harrowsmith article "Building by the Book" by Craig Canine, a handwritten note to Garreau, "Changing tack on the timeless way" by Reyner Banham, a thank you note from Christopher Alexander to the American Institute of Architects and "The Winds of Windsorism" by Herbert Muschamp. Theory
  - Silicon Valley Architecture, February 1984 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    A special section of the San Jose Mercury News about Silicon Valley Architecture. Theory
  - Architects (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Book chapters and newspaper and magazine articles about architects. Theory
  - Prince Charles Quote, December 1987 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    A quote from Charles, Prince of Wales about property development. Theory
  - Robert Charles Lesser Co. Seattle, December 1991 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    An overview of the Seattle market.
  - Somerset, New Jersey, Undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
    Document about Somerset, NJ.
  - Somerset Alliance for the Future, Undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
    A description of the Somerset Alliance for the Future.
  - Tennessee, March 1992 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    A real estate review of Nashville, TN.
  - Stephen Fox 19th Century Attitudes, May 1990 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    A newspaper article about Houston architecture.
  - Texas Architect Magazine, May-June 1990 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    The May-June 1990 issue of Texas Architect Magazine.
  - Uptown Houston, October 1984-October 1988 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    Documents about architecture in uptown Houston, Texas.
  - Fame City, October 1988 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    A review of an arcade in Houston, Texas.
  - Dallas Sources, Undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
    Notes about Dallas.
  - Dallas Market Reports, June 1990 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Real estate reports for the Dallas market.
  - Las Colinas, January-February 1988 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Pamphlets and promotional materials for Las Colinas, a planned community in Irving, Texas.
  - Gary Carwright's Las Colinas Piece, October 1987 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    A Texas Monthly article by Gary Cartwright about Las Colinas.
  - Las Colinas, February-June 1988 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    Documents about Las Colinas, a planned community in Irving, Texas.
  - The Woodlands, 1987-February 1990 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    "The Woodlands: New Community Development, 1964-1983" by George T. Morgan and John O. King, and "The Role of The Woodlands in the Economic Development of Montgomery County" by Barton A. Smith.
  - Galleria Richard West Piece, July 1980 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    "My Home The Galleria" by Richard West from the July 1980 issue of Texas Monthly.
  - Gerald D. Hines, 1957-1987 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    "Gerald D. Hines Interests Experience Record". A list of construction projects undertaken by Gerald D. Hines Interests.
  - Tucson, Arizona, February 1989 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    Notes, pamphlets, magazines and essays about Tucson, Arizona.
  - Tucson Arizona Restaurants and Attractions, December 1988-January 1989 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    Magazines and notes about activities in Tucson, Arizona.
  - Toronto, April 1987-January 1989 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    Magazines, article transcripts, notes, correspondence, and newspaper clippings about Toronto. Also included is "Building A Consensus the Canadian Way" and "North American Culture".
  - AMLI Barrett, October 1992-January 1994 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    Advertisements, development summaries, promotional material, articles, maps, census information and aerial photographs for Barrett real estate and AMLI Realty Co. in the Atlanta Georgia area. Also included is a business card, "The Power of One Dollar" and a Cobb chamber newspaper.
  - Regional Commission Atlanta, May 1989 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    Documents about growth in Atlanta from the Atlanta Regional Commission and the Atlanta Regional Commission 1989 Annual Report.
  - Guilford Forest, December 1988 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    Documents about Guilford Forest, a planned community in South Fulton, Georgia. Material includes pricing information, floor plans, a history of Guilford Forest, maps and lot descriptions.
  - Washington Region Market Reports, April 1987-March 1990 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Documents, real estate reports, market reports, article transcripts and magazine articles about Washington, DC development.
  - Alexandria, January 1987 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    A newspaper clipping, a pamphlet and transcripts of articles about development in Alexandria, Virginia.
  - Alexandria Railyard, September 1988 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    A Washington Post article about a rail yard in Alexandria, Virginia.
  - LA Market Prices, January 1987 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    A Los Angeles Real Estate Market report.
  - Regional Office Cores LA Metro, August 1989 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    A map, statistics and analysis of office cores in the Southern California region.
  - LA Times Magazine LA vs Orange County, June 1990 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    An issue of LA Times Magazine.
  - Kotkin Clips LA, February 1988-March 1989 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Two articles by Joel Kotkin.
  - Marketing to the New America LA, July 1987 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    An Inc. Magazine article "Marketing to the New America" by Joel Kotkin.
  - LA Economy Entering the 21st Century, July 1988 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    A magazine about the LA area economy.
  - Jeffrey Ullman LA, September 1990 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    Transcript of notes about Jeffrey Ullman.
  - Bob Kelley LA, Undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
    Notes.
  - LA Times Magazine, November 1989 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    An LA Times Magazine article by Joel Kotkin "Fear and Reality in LA Melting Pot".
  - Best of Business Quarterly LA, March 1989-February 1990 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    Two magazine articles about LA business.
  - LA Magazine, July 1990 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    30th anniversary issue of Los Angeles Magazine.
  - California Housing Stump, October 1989 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    Forbes Magazine article about a housing slump in LA.
  - Moral Issues in New Town Development LA, February 1970 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    A document about development in LA.
  - To Live and Write in LA, January 1990 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    A Book World article about writing in LA.
  - Newsweek Clip California, July 1989 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    A Newsweek article about California.
  - LA Comes of Age, January 1988 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    An Atlantic article "LA Comes of Age".
  - LA City of the Future in Trouble, June 1989 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    A Wall Street Journal article about LA in trouble.
  - LA Reason Report, September-October 1991 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    Reason Report issue with an article about LA.
  - Detroit Oil Prices, April 1990 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    A Washington Post article about oil prices.
  - Detroit Fisher Building, November-December 1990 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    A newsletter from the Fisher, Albert Kahn, New Center One Buildings.
  - Detroit General, November 1990 (Box 13, Folder 24)
    Notes and newspaper clippings about Detroit, Michigan.
  - Ford Motor Land Development Corporation, January 1990 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    Documents and news releases about the Ford Motor Land Development Corporation.
  - Denver, June 1991 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    A New York Times article about professional baseball in Denver, Colorado.
  - Notes Detroit, July 1989 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    Notes about Detroit, Michigan and notes for Walking Magazine.
  - Notes Detroit, May 1989-November 1990 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    Notes and article transcripts about Detroit, Michigan.
  - CB Commercial Chicago, April-May 1993 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Documents, market reports, press releases and maps about Chicago from CB Commercial.
  - CRS Report for Congress 1990, April-July 1990 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    Congressional Research Service reports on rural economy and a business card. Problems/Solutions
  - Philly Redevelopment Businesses Relocate Within City, December 1988 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    A Philadelphia Inquirer article about business relocation. Problems/Solutions
  - Redevelopment Slums Philly, November 1988 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    A Philadelphia Inquirer article about the development of slums in Philadelphia. Problems/Solutions
  - Redevelopment Union Station, September 1988 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    Newspaper articles and a pamphlet about the renovation of Union Station in Washington, DC. Problems/Solutions
  - Redevelopment Waterfront Philly, December 1988 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Documents about the Philadelphia waterfront. Problems/Solutions
  - Redevelopment Waterfront Camden, November 1988 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    A Philadelphia Inquirer article about Camden, New Jersey. Problems/Solutions
  - Retail - Customer Service John Tschohl, Undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    An interview with John Tschohl. Problems/Solutions
  - E.M. Risse, December 1988-Aril 1991 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    Documents and notes from and about E.M. Risse and Synergy Planning. Problems/Solutions
  - James Rouse, December 1976-July 1989 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    Documents about James Rouse and his work in city planning. Problems/Solutions
  - Suburbs Detroit, 1980-June 1988 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    Documents about traffic, shopping and Urban Geography in suburban Detroit. Problems/Solutions
  - Training, Undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
    A Wall Street Journal article about training in the workplace. Problems/Solutions
  - Population Movement, January 1989 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    A New York Times article about the growth of the suburbs. Problems/Solutions
  - Satellite Imaging, November 1988 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    An information packet from Earth Observation Satellite Company about satellite imaging. Problems/Solutions
  - Trends Future, July-October 1989 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    Documents about the future of development. Problems/Solutions
  - Trends Flex Space, May 1987 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    A Washington Post article about the use of office space. Problems/Solutions
  - Universities, June 1989 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    A Washington Post article about schools' land development. Problems/Solutions
  - Third Summit of the World's Major Cities, Montreal 1991, October 1991 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    Faxes about a meeting about the worlds major cities.
  - Video Conferencing, January 1989 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    A Washington Post article about video conferencing. Problems/Solutions
  - Working at Home, December 1989 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    A Wall Street Journal article about working from home. Problems/Solutions
  - Atlanta Tribune Black Business Owners, June 1989-April 1990 (Box 14, Folder 21 (Oversize Box 65))
    Issues of the Atlanta Tribune and articles about African American business owners. OVERSIZE BOX 65
  - Atlanta Tribune, September 1989-March 1990 (Box 14, Folder 22 (Oversize Box 65))
    Issues of the Atlanta Tribune with articles about business. OVERSIZE BOX 65
  - Atlanta Tribune, April 1987-July 1989 (Box 14, Folder 23 (Oversize Box 65))
    Issues of the Atlanta Tribune with articles about women in business. OVERSIZE BOX 65
  - Meadowlands Corporate Center, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    An information packet about real estate in Lyndhurst, New Jersey.
  - Eaglerock - Roseland, NJ, Undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    A promotional booklet for Eaglerock, a private club in Roseland, New Jersey.
  - Somerset Hills Roseland, NJ, Undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    Real estate information about office buildings in the Somerset Hills Corporate Center.
  - Chester, NJ, November 1984-January 1992 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    Documents about land use, the future, population and the economy in Chester County, New Jersey.
  - New Jersey Sources, Undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
    Three business cards from New Jersey.
  - New York Market Report Offices, July 1988-September 1989 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    New York Real Estate reports.